# 是起泡泡了 这糖化了
The sauce is bubbling. Yes, because the sugar melted and dissolved.
# 关键时刻
It is the important moment.
# 出锅了啊
Let’s serve the dish.
# 今天大爷给大家做一道 咕咾虾球
Today, Da Ye will teach you how to make the sweet and sour shrimp.
# 在家庭里边做这道菜就比较简单
It is easy to cook this dish at home.
# 先把这虾从脊背给它剖开
We first need to cut the shrimp on its back,
# 剖开当中我们就查查有没有沙线
and get rid of the intestine if you saw it.
# 这还是挺干净的 对
It looks clean. Yes, it is.
# 很多网友上次对大妈的录像水平
Regarding to Da Ma’s filming skills in the last video, lots of friends
# 非常满意
are very satisfied.
# 不是非常满意
It was not ‘very’satisfied.
# 是非常非常的满意
It was ‘extremely’ satisfied.
# 据说比二伯录的好
They said that Da Ma did a better job than Er Bai.
# 一会给大妈露个镜头
Let’s shoot Da Ma later,
# 让网友们看看大妈什么样
So that our online friends can meet Da Ma.
# 不可以
No, you can’t do that.
# 不行啊
No?
# 身份不能暴露 还在隐蔽当中
We should keep your identity as a secret.
# 顶多我就是老饭骨的家属
I am just a family member of Lao Fan Gu.
# 把这虾从脊背开
We need to cut this shrimp on its back,
# 但是不让它断了 对不能断
But we don’t want to cut through it. Yes, we shouldn’t cut the shrimp in half.
# 因为咕咾虾是一个圆球状
Because we want the shrimp to become sphere-like.
# 好了以后我们要把它洗一洗
Ok, let’s rinse the shrimps.
# 我看你这儿还有什么 番茄沙司
Let me see what do we have here, tomato sauce.
# 有番茄酱是最好
It would be better to use tomato sauce.
# 搁点盐 这叫底味
Let’s put some salt in it. We called it ‘flavor base’.
# 胡椒粉 还是白胡椒
Put some white pepper powder,
# 黄酒
And cooking wine.
# 这酒得省着使
We shouldn’t waste the cooking wine.
# 能多用一次就多用一次
It would be great if we can even get one more use out of this bottle.
# 如果要求高一点我们还得搁个葱
If you would like to achieve a better flavor, we need to put some green onions.
# 去掉虾的腥味
This marinade will get rid of the unpleasant smell in shrimp.
# 葱段和姜片
Put the green onions and ginger in the bowl.
# 腌的时候不搁淀粉吧
Do we need any starch while marinating?
# 搁么 暂时不搁 待会再抓粉
Not now, but we will need some later.
# 这黄瓜不去皮
We will keep the cucumber skin on.
# 要这个绿色 切成滚刀块
The green color will make our dish pretty. Now let’s cut it into big pieces.
# 别太多啊
We don’t need too many cucumber.
# 胡萝卜
Carrot.
# 也切成滚刀块 跟那一样的切法
We need to cut the carrot the same way as the cucumber.
# 胡萝卜为了一会方便
In order to make the carrot cook quickly, we will
# 给它出下水
blanch it first.
# 这儿有一电磁炉 焯一下
There is an induction cooker. We will use it to blanch the carrot.
# 然后切点小料 葱
Let’s cut some other ingredients, spring onion.
# 不要芯儿啊 这点葱就够了
You don’t want the center of the spring onion? No, it's enough.
# 大妈监管的还挺严格
Da Ma is supervising strictly.
# 你别给我糟践了
I don’t want you to waste the spring onion.
# 网友上次对您的评价挺高的
Online friends thought you did a great job last time.
# 真的吗 那太高兴了
Really? I am very happy.
# 还得好好努力
I will keep trying hard.
# 做糖醋的不能少蒜
When we make the sweet and sour sauce, we mustn't forget garlic.
# 先拍后切 让它碎一点 蒜末
We first need to crush it, then mince it.
# 今天咱基本上不是家庭版
This version is not only for home-cooking,
# 基本就是饭店的
It can even be used in restaurants.
# 咕咾虾 咕咾肉 咕咾鸡球
You can use this method to cook shrimp, pork or chicken.
# 这都行 叫一通百通
It all works – so called ‘master the one to master all’.
# 其实这道菜原始的叫咕咾肉
Actually, the original of this dishes is called ‘Sweet and sour pork’.
# 来点姜米
Let’s put some minced ginger.
# 这就是传统做法是吗
Is this a traditional way of cooking?
# 只不过食材不一样了
Yes, but the ingredients are different.
# 网友在家里抗YQ
Online friends stay at home in response to the pandemic.
# 我们都在行动
We also need to support them.
# 行动什么啊 吃点好的
What could we do? Cook and eat something tasty.
# 胡萝卜焯水好了
We have blanched the carrots.
# 因为这虾里边有水
Because there is some water in the shrimps,
# 我们先抓点粉子 少抓
We only need a little of the starch.
# 葱姜拣出来
Let’s take the spring onions and ginger out.
# 抓点淀粉 让每个虾球都粘上
Then we add some starch and make sure every shrimp have some starch on its surface.
# 这叫水淀粉
It is called ‘starch slurry’.
# 因为它里面有水
Because there is some water in the bowl.
# 但是这个是不用加水和它是吧
We don’t need water to mix with the starch, do we?
# 因为这虾本身就有水分
No, because the shrimps contain water.
# 咱就别弄的太稀了起不到作用 挂不上
We don’t want the slurry to be thin, otherwise, it would be hard to stick on the shrimps.
# 现在这粉子合适了
The amount of the starch is just about right.
# 下面咱们开始蘸粉子
Now we need to dip the shrimp in more starch.
# 打开了不打开 还得攥呢
Do we need to uncurl the shrimps? No, we need to shape them into spheres.
# 得攥成小球似的
So that they will be shaped like a ball.
# 咕咾肉用的猪肉 最好用点肥瘦的
If you are using pork here, you should choose the cut with some fat.
# 我们也可以用这种方法腌好了 蘸淀粉
For pork, we can also use the same method of marinating and dipping into the starch.
# 鸡胸肉也好吃
Chicken breast would also work.
# 咕咾鸡球 咕咾虾球 咕咾肉
You can make sweet and sour chicken, shrimp, and pork.
# 因为它是球状的
Because it is shaped like a ball.
# 这叫先成型
We called this step as ‘forming the shape’.
# 一会要定型
Then we will help them hold the shape later.
# 好了 下边开始炸
Ok, now we can start deep-frying.
# 这油也是一样 别放太多
We don’t need too much oil.
# 介绍介绍调料
Let me introduce the ingredients for the sauce.
# 酒 盐 胡椒 白糖 番茄酱
We have cooking wine, salt, white pepper, sugar, ketchup.
# 这个不容易看到 这是白醋
and white vinegar. It is hard to show on the camera.
# 外焦里嫩 甜酸适口
The outside of this dish will be crispy and the inside will be juicy. The balance between the sweetness and sourness is perfect.
# 看着啊 我们这个油差不多了
See, the temperature of the oil is about right.
# 咱们再固定固定
Let’s shape the shrimp again before we put it in the oil.
# 再攥一下
Squeeze it.
# 大爷干什么都那么认真
Whatever Da Ye does, he is very serious and careful,
# 做起饭也是特别认真
especially when he is cooking.
# 我这是从小攥煤球长大的
I used to shape the coal briquettes a lot when I was young.
# 我可以俩手攥
I could shape it with both of my hands.
# 大妈给看着锅里边啊 它在不断地变化
Da Ma, please keep an eye on the wok. The shrimps are changing temperature constantly.
# 圆呼吧 圆呼了
Does it look like a ball? Yes.
# 越大越好看是吧 变黄了
The shrimps are prettier when they are getting bigger. The color is changing to yellow.
# 别老照菜照照大爷
Da Ma, don't just record the dish, record me too.
# 不照你人家也知道是你
Online friends know who you are even if I didn’t give you any shots.
# 上次网友评价咱们做那什么的时候
Online friends comment a lot when we made the pies last time.
# 网友评价的很多 上千条
We received thousands of comments.
# 有夸我的 夸你
Some complimented me, and some complimented you.
# 还夸大妈的呢 大妈不行
Really? Did they complimented me as well? I don’t deserve it.
# 大妈就是绿叶 你才是那红花
Da Ma is like the leaf to the flower, Da Ye is the flower.
# 我是那花儿啊
Am I the flower?
# 这就好啦 没呢这还得复油一遍
Are we done? No, we need to deep fry it the second time.
# 老炸就炸干了
If we cook the shrimps for too long, it will be less juicy.
# 然后再来油温让它稍微调整一下
Let’s heat up the oil first and then fry it again.
# 再高一些 高一点
The temperature need to be higher.
# 先控控油
We want to strain the oil off.
# 这是复炸 复炸一遍
This is the second time we fry the shrimps.
# 你看炸完以后更好看是啊
You see, the shrimps looks better after the second frying.
# 这就好了 真是好 都想吃了
It is done. It looks great. I want to eat it now.
# 这时候来点底油
Now, we need some oil.
# 大妈稍微把火小着点儿
Da Ma, could you help me to turn the heat lower?
# 葱姜蒜 胡萝卜黄瓜
Let’s put the spring onion, ginger, garlic, carrot, cucumber,
# 番茄酱 番茄沙司
And ketchup in the wok.
# 炒一炒 搁上水
We now need to stir fry it, and then add some water.
# 番茄酱要多炒一会
If we are using tomato sauce, we need to cook a bit longer.
# 这番茄沙司不用多炒 因为它是熟酱
But we are using ketchup here, we don’t need to cook for too long, because it is already cooked.
# 开大火 咱们开始加调料
Turn on high heat. Let’s add some flavoring:
# 加点盐 大约四克
4g of salt.
# 要想甜 要加盐
The salt will enhance the sweetness.
# 白糖 搁那么多糖啊 糖要多一点
Sugar. Wow, do we need to put so much sugar? Yes, we need a quite a lot of sugar.
# 搁了这汁儿才亮
The sauce will be glossy because of the sugar.
# 不会齁儿的慌啊 不会
Will it be too sweet? No.
# 糖少了它不会产生气泡
If we don’t have enough sugar, the sauce will not be bubbling.
# 网友我们要是在家里做的时候说
Some friends tried the dishes at home and asked
# 这汁怎么出来以后不够亮啊
Why is the sauce not glossy enough?
# 就是你的糖不够
It is because you didn’t use enough sugar.
# 白醋 白醋也就两勺 两勺羹
Now we add two spoons of white vinegar.
# 有的可能说我喜欢吃番茄
Some people may like the tomatoes flavor:
# 颜色还可以重一点  再多放一点
You can add a bit more ketchup to darken the color.
# 现在这汁已经调好了 勾个芡
Now the sauce is ready, let’s thicken it by adding the starch slurry.
# 是起泡泡了 起泡了吧
It is bubbling now. Yes, I said it would be bubbling, right?
# 这糖化了 所以你调出来这汁才发亮
The sauce will be shiny when the sugar melted.
# 看着啊 这是淀粉
See, it is starch slurry.
# 给准备一盘儿
Please prepare a plate for me.
# 这可以吧 那就可以了
How about this? It looks good.
# 看着啊 下去了啊 亮了
Look at it -  I put the starch slurry in the sauce, and the sauce is glossy now.
# 关键时刻
Important moment.
# 出锅了啊 好
It is done. Good.
# 倍儿红 颠一颠 蘸匀了
The color is bright red. Let’s toss it around, so that the sauce will be evenly distributed.
# 好了出锅了
Ok, we can take it out of the wok.
# 大妈给照一相片啊 那是肯定得照
Da Ma, take a picture. For sure!
# 真好
It looks great!
# 稍等稍等 调整一下
Wait a moment, I need to adjust the plating.
# 酸甜可口的咕咾虾
Sweet and sour shrimp, it tastes really good.
# 它形状是球状 那就是咕咾虾球
It looks like a ball, so we call it sweet and sour shrimp ball.
# 上菜
Finished!
# 家有大厨 就是幸福
It is awesome to have a chef at home!
# 我总也忘不了这句话
I always want to say this slogan.
# import ending.srt 00:08:37,000 请原样保留此行